A Guide to the Scott family papers, 1867-1931
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Scott family papers, 1867-1931
The Library of Virginia
43713
1.575 cu. ft. and 4 boxes
Scott family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Johnny Scott of Somerset, Orange County, Virginia.
Biographical Information
William Wallace Scott (1845-1929) attended the Virginia Military Institute and enlisted in the Confederate Army 1 December 1863, serving in Company H, 4th Virginia Cavalry, also known as the Black Horse Cavalry. Scott was captured by Union forces in April 1865, but escaped; eventually being paroled in Charlottesville, Virginia, on 1 May 1865. After the war, Scott became a lawyer and editor. He served as the law librarian for the state of Virginia, and published works on Virginia and its history. Scott married Claudia Marshall Willis (1846-1912) 29 September 1869, and they had nine children. One of those nine children was Philip Henshaw Scott (1873-1962) who served as a career United States Coast Guard officer who served aboard Coast Guard cutters, including commanding the U.S.S. Seminole. Philip Scott also served in ports such as Norfolk, Virginia, and Sault Ste. Marie, Michigan. He married Mattie Moore Leitch (1875-1953) 29 April 1903, and they had five children: Philip Henshaw Scott (1904-1914), William Wallace Scott (1906-1931), Martha Moore Scott (1908-1979), Meredith Leitch Scott (1915-2002), and Johnny Scott (1918-). Most members of the Scott family are buried in Maplewood Cemetery in Gordonsville, Virginia.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1867-1931, of the Scott family of Orange County and Richmond, Virginia, consisting of accounts, address books, check stubs, clippings, correspondence, drawings, flight journals and logs, insurance policies, judicial records, lists, military passes, negatives, phototgraphs, poems, postcards, promissory notes, publications, report cards, tax records, telegrams, visiting cards, and other papers. Papers concern the personal lives and professional careers of Philip Henshaw Scott (1873-1962), Mattie Moore Leitch Scott (1875-1953), his father W. W. Scott (1845-1929), and his children, including William Wallace Scott (1906-1931).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1867, 1898-1931.
Series II: Accounts, receipts, etc. 1912-1925.
Series III: William Wallace Scott papers, 1924-1931.
Series IV: General papers.
Series V: Publications and articles.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
W. W. Scott papers, 1891-1957 (LVA accession 44929, 50464).
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1867-1931., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 1-2)
  Correspondence, 1867-1931, consisting of letters between Philip H. Scott and his wife Mattie Moore Leitch Scott regarding his career as an officer in the United States Coast Guard and his various ports of service; Mattie Scott's raising their family and social news; the family homes in Orange County, Virginia; W. W. Scott's professional career; and the lives of Philip and Mattie Scott's children, including the health of William (Billy) Wallace Scott. Also includes corrrespondence from W. W. Scott, William (Billy) Wallace Scott, Martha Scott, Meredith Scott, Johnny Scott, and other relatives containing personal, family, and social news. Correspondence also contains letters from friends to the Scott family, as well as professional correspondence to Scott from fellow Coast Guard officers.
  - Letters, 1867. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1898. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1900. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1903. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1908. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1912. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1913. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1914. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters, 1915. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters, 1916. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters, 1917-1918. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters, February-July 1919. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters, August-December 1919. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters, 1921. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters, February-August 1922. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters, September-December 1922. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letters, January-February 1923. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letters, March-June 1923. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letters, August-December 1923. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letters, January-April 1924. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letters, May-June 1924. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letters, July-August 1924. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letters, September 1924. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Letters, 1-18 October 1924. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Letters, 20-23 October 1924. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Letters, January-February 1925. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Letters, March 1925. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Letters, April-July 1925. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Letters, November-December 1925. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Letters, 1926. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Letters, January-February 1927. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Letters, May-June 1927. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Letters, July 1927. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters, August-September 1927. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters, November-December 1927. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1928. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1929. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1930. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letters, February-June 1931. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letters, July 1931. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Letters, 3-10 August 1931. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letters, 11-14 August 1931. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Letters, 17-19 August 1931. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Letters, 24-27 August 1931. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Letters, 10-13 September 1931. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Letter, Philip Scott to Mattie Scott. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Letters, Mattie Scott to Philip Scott. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Letters, W. W. (Billy) Scott to Philip Scott. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Letters, John, Martha, and W. W. (Billy) Scott to their mother Mattie Scott. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Letters to Philip Scott. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Letters to Mattie Scott. (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Series II: Accounts, receipts, etc., 1912-1925., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 2-3)
  Accounts, receipts, etc., 1912-1925, contains accounts, check stubs, deposit slips, insurance policies, promissory notes, receipts, tax records, and other papers regarding purchases of items and services by Philip Scott and Mattie Scott in Elizabeth City and Wilmington, North Carolina; Norfolk, Virginia; Sault Ste. Marie, Michigan; Baltimore, Maryland; and elsewhere. Includes school accounts for William Wallace Scott at ChristChurch School in Middlesex County, Virginia, and for Martha Scott at Stuart Hall in Staunton, Virginia.
  - Receipts, the Duff Company (Elizabeth City, North Carolina), 1916-1917. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Application and bills, Elizabeth City Electric Light and Power Company (Elizabeth City, North Carolina), 1916-1917. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Receipts, Elizabeth City, North Carolina, post office, 1916. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Receipts, Elizabeth City Sewage Company (Elizabeth City, North Carolina), 1916-1917. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Accounts, Elizabeth City Water and Power Company (Elizabeth City, North Carolina), 1916-1917. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Accounts [V. M.] Jenkins and Company (Elizabeth City, North Carolina), 1916-1917. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Accounts, business cars, Keeney Crank (Elizabeth City, North Carolina), 1916. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Accounts, M. G. Wright (Elizabeth City, North Carolina), 1916-1917. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Accounts, McCabe and Grice (Elizabeth City, North Carolina), 1916. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Accounts, Mitchell's Department Store (Elizabeth City, North Carolina), 1916-1917. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Contracts, receipts, accounts, Norfolk and Carolina Telephone and Telegraph (Elizabeth City, North Carolina), 1916-1917. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Accounts, Parker Brothers (Elizabeth City, North Carolina), 1916-1917. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Accounts, R. E. Quinn and Company (Elizabeth City, North Carolina), 1916. (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Accounts, Rucker and Sheely (Elizabeth City, North Carolina), 1916-1917. (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Accounts, S. S. Davis (Elizabeth City, North Carolina), 1916-1917. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Account books, drafts, receipts, promissory notes, and papers, Savings Bank and Trust Company (Elizabeth City, North Carolina), 1916-1923. (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Accounts, receipts, Sharber and White Hardware Company (Elizabeth City, North Carolina), 1916-1917. (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Bills, Southern Gas Improvement Company (Elizabeth City, North Carolina), 1916-1917. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Accounts, receipts, W. S. White and Company (Elizabeth City, North Carolina), 1916-1917. (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Accounts, receipts, and papers, Albemarle Laundry, Cooper Cleaning Works, E. S. Cheeson Company, Eastern Carolina Transportation Company, Fred Davis the Old Coal Dealer, Lavenstein's Department Store, Owens Shoe Company, P. W. Melick Company, Scott and Twiddy's (Dean's) (all Elizabeth City, North Carolina), 1916-1917. (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Personal accounts of Mattie Scott while living in Elizabeth City, North Carolina, 1916-1917. (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Series III: William Wallace Scott papers, 1924-1931., Extent: 1 box. (Box 3)
  Papers, 1924-1931, of William Wallace Scott (1906-1931) consisting of grade cards from ChristChurch School and the United States Coast Guard Academy; aviator's flight log and flight journal, 1929-1930, recording Scott's activities as a pilot; a physical exam for flying; a bank deposit slip; calling cards; and an address book.
  - Aviator's flight log book, 1929-1930. (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Series IV: General papers., Extent: 1 box. (Box 3)
  General papers contain Coast Guard papers including a list of officers, Naval Yard pass, and court case papers; drawings including a sketch of Johnny Scott; excerpts from Flavius Vegetius' De Re Militari (On The Rules of War); Scott family photographs; postcards; and general papers including lists, poems, and other papers.
  - Philip Scott--Coast Guard. (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Series V: Publications and articles., Extent: 1 box. (Box 4)
  Publications and articles include copies of A Vindication of Edmund Randolph, Some Observations on Political Parties in Virginia, and Virginia Principles owned by W. W. Scott (1845-1929) and including his annotations; brochures for Scott's History of Orange County, Va.; a copy of Shakespeare's The Merry Wives of Windsor; Constitution and By-laws of the United States Coast Guard Academy Alumni Association; Digest of Important General Game and Fish Laws of Michigan; and Rules for the St. Mary's River. Also included are articles on the Coast Guard and Prohibition.
  - A Vindication of Edmund Randolph edited by P. V. Daniel. (Box 4, Folder 1)